{
  "reference_number": "1082",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Methane from livestock on pasture is NOT a greenhouse gas. Ruminants are part of the grassland ecology and have been for 10s of\n millions of years before man appeared on the scene. The deepest deposits of soil carbon all happened on grasslands. Management\n\n to mimic the huge herbivore herds will do the same today. This is the only effective tool we have to reverse desertification over 60%\n of earths land area."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "in any situation it should be net emissions. Grazing animals do not live in a research tent but are part of a complex ecology where\n\n everything cycles. Measuring part of the cycle is plain goofy. Similarly pine trees are not just carbon accumulators but if planted into\n grassland lose all the soil carbon which is initially there. It is illogical to pitch ecological systems against each other to have an ETS. It\n is anthropological global warming and living systems are too complex to allow for accurate accounting. Instead pay attention to\n\n management. and ensure that maximising carbon sequestration in soil and biomass is part of the context for decision making. A\n vibrant healthy environment will ensue."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is early days, we are dealing with complex issues and the chances of getting things right are pretty low."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "BUt livestock methane is NOT a CHG and so DO NOT comprise 48%. Before the industrial revolution methane varied between 600\n and 800 ppm (in spite of unfathomable numbers of ruminants). In the 1980s it rose to 1300ppm attributable to leaks in the trans\n Siberian gas pipeline. Since 200 it has risen to 2300ppm thanks to fracking."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "It is arrogantly delusional to think a budget will not need revision. All budgets need revising from time to time."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Methane from ruminants on pasture is not a CHG therefore all assumptions are wrong. Only Net emissions from the whole ecology\n\ncan be relevant. 10 % more of NZ land area in pine trees is hardly a creative outcome."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "GET IT RIGHT. Natural systems are complex. All are cyclical systems. Calling just one part a source or sink is frankly gibberish."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Providing the goals are sensible"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "You must include ecologists trained to see live as patterns. After all ruminants do not exist in isolation from their environment. Net\n\nemissions are greatly influenced by management and this needs to be where the attention goes. Industrial scientists are OK for\nindustrial emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "In agriculture it is management that determines whether the farm is a net source or sink. We either degrade the land or regenerate\ndepending on grazing policies. Regeneration sequesters carbon in soil and increased biomass. Same applies for forestry and\nhorticulture. To say a cow burps methane and a tree is made of wood is grossly over simplistic. If your best solution is more radiata\n\npine monocultures and all the negative environmental consequences of that we are truly devoid of imagination."
    }
  ]
}
